Poul Anderson

The Horn Of Time The Hunter

Now and then, on that planet, Jong Errifrans thought he heard the distant blowing of a horn. It would begin low, with a pulse that quickened as the notes waxed„until the snarl broke in a brazen scream and sank sobbing away. The first time he started and asked the others if they heard. But the sound was on the bare edge of audibility for him, whose ears were young and sharp, and the men said no. “Some trick of the wind, off in the cliffs yonder,” Mons Rainart suggested. He shivered. “The damned wind is always hunting here.” Jong did not mention it again, but when he heard the noise thereafter a jag of cold went through him.

There was no reason for that. Nothing laired in the city but seabirds, whose wings made a white storm over the tower tops and whose flutings mingled with wind skirl and drum roll of surf; nothing more sinister had appeared than a great tiger-striped fish, which patrolled near the outer reefs. And perhaps that was why Jong feared the horn: it gave the emptiness a voice.

At night, rather than set up their glower, the four would gather wood and give themselves the primitive comfort of a fire. Their camping place was in what might once have been a forum. Blocks of polished stone thrust out of the sand and wiry grass that had occupied all streets; toppled colonnades demarked a square. More shelter was offered by the towers clustered in the city’s heart, still piercing the sky, the glasite windows still unbroken. But no, these windows were too much like a dead man’s eyes, the rooms within were too hushed, now that the machines that had been the city’s life lay corroded beneath the dunes. It was better to raise a tent under the stars. Those, at least, were much the same, after twenty thousand years.

The men would eat, and then Regor Lannis, the leader, would lift his communicator bracelet near his mouth and report their day’s ransacking. The space-boat’s radio caught the message and relayed it to the Golden Flyer, which orbited with the same period as the planet’s twenty-one-hour rotation, so that she was always above this island. “Very little news,” Regor typically said. “Remnants of tools and so on. We haven’t found any bones yet for a radioactivity dating. I don’t think we will, either. They probably cremated their dead, to the very end. Mons has estimated that engine block we found began rusting some ten thousand years ago. He’s only guessing, though. It wouldn’t have lasted at all if the sand hadn’t buried it, and we don’t know when that happened.

“But you say the furnishings inside the towers are mostly intact, age-proof alloys and synthetics,” answered Captain Ilmaray’s voice. “Can’t you deduce anything from their, well, their arrangement or disarrangement? If the city was plundered—”

“No, sir, the signs are too hard to read. A lot of rooms have obviously been stripped. But we don’t know whether that was done in one day or over a period maybe of centuries, as the last colonists mined their homes for stuff they could no longer make. We can only be sure, from the dust, that no one’s been inside for longer than I like to think about.”

When Regor had signed off, Jong would usually take out his guitar and chord the songs they sang, the immemorial songs of the Kith, many translated from languages spoken before ever men left Earth. It helped drown out the wind and the surf, booming down on the beach where once a harbor had stood. The fire flared high, picking their faces out of night, tinging plain work clothes with unrestful red, and then guttering down so that shadows swallowed the bodies. They looked much alike, those four men, small, lithe, with sharp, dark features; for the Kith were a folk apart, marrying between their own ships, which carried nearly all traffic among the stars. Since a vessel might be gone from Earth for a century or more, the planetbound civilizations, flaring and dying and reborn like the flames that warmed them now, could not be theirs. The men differed chiefly in age, from the sixty years that furrowed Regor Lannis’s skin to the twenty that Jong Errifrans had marked not long ago.

Ship’s years, mostly, Jong remembered, and looked up to the Milky Way with a shudder. When you fled at almost the speed of light, time shrank for you, and in his own life he had seen the flower and the fall of an empire. He had not thought much about it then—it was the way of things, that the Kith should be quasi-immortal and the planetarians alien, transitory, not quite real. But a voyage of ten thousand light-years toward galactic center, and back, was more than anyone had ventured before; more than anyone would ever have done, save to expiate the crime of crimes. Did the Kith still exist? Did Earth?

After some days, Regor decided: “We’d better take a look at the hinterland. We may improve our luck.”

“Nothing in the interior but forest and savannah,” Neri Avelair objected. “We saw that from above.”

“On foot, though, you see items you miss from a boat,” Regor said. “The colonists can’t have lived exclusively in places like this. They’d need farms, mines, extractor plants, outlying settlements. If we could examine one of those, we might find clearer indications than in this damned huge warren.”

“How, much chance would we have, hacking our way through the brush?” Neri argued. “I say let’s investigate some of those other towns we spotted.”

“They’re more mined yet,” Mons Rainart reminded him. “Largely submerged.” He need not have spoken; how could they forget? Land does not sink fast. The fact that the sea was eating the cities gave some idea of how long they had been abandoned.

“Just so.” Regor nodded. “I don’t propose plunging into the woods, either. That’d need more men and more time than we can spare. But there’s an outsize beach about a hundred kilometers north of here, fronting on a narrow-mouthed bay, with fertile hills right behind—hills that look as if they ought to contain ores. I’d be surprised if the colonists did not exploit the area.”

Neri’s mouth twitched downward. His voice was not quite steady. “How long do we have to stay on this ghost planet before we admit we’ll never know what happened?”

“Not too much longer,” Regor said. “But we’ve got to try our best before we do leave.”

He jerked a thumb at the city. Its towers soared above fallen walls and marching dunes into a sky full of birds. The bright yellow sun had bleached out their pastel colors, leaving them bone-white. And yet the view on their far side was beautiful, forest that stretched inland a hundred shades of shadow-rippled green, while in the opposite direction the land sloped down to a sea that glittered like emerald strewn with diamond dust, moving and shouting and hurling itself in foam against the reefs. The first generations here must have been very happy, Jong thought.

“Something destroyed them, and it wasn’t simply a war,” Regor said. “We need to know what. It may not have affected any other world. But maybe it did.”

Maybe Earth lay as empty, Jong thought, not for the lust time.

The Golden Flyer had paused here to refit before venturing back into man’s old domain. Captain Ilmaray had chosen an F9 star arbitrarily, three hundred light-years from Sol’s calculated present position. They detected no whisper of the energies used by civilized races, who might have posed a threat. The third planet seemed a paradise, Earth-mass but with its land scattered in islands around a global ocean, warm from pole to pole. Mons Rainart was surprised that the carbon dioxide equilibrium was maintained with so little exposed rock. Then he observed weed mats everywhere on the waters, many of them hundreds of square kilometers in area, and decided that their photosynthesis was active enough to produce a Terrestrial-type atmosphere.

The shock had been to observe from orbit the ruined cities. Not that colonization could not have reached this far, and beyond, during twenty thousand years. But the venture had been terminated; why?

That evening it was Jong’s turn to hold a personal conversation with those in the mother ship. He got his parents, via intercom, to tell them how he fared, The heart jumped in his breast when Sorya Rainart’s voice joined theirs. “Oh yes,” the girl said, with an uneven little laugh, “I’m right here in the apartment. Dropped in for a visit, by chance.”

Her brother chuckled at Jong’s back. The young man flushed and wished hotly for privacy. But of course Sorya would have known he’d call tonight . . . . If the Kith still lived, there could be nothing between him and her. You brought your wife home from another ship. It was spaceman’s law, exogamy aiding a survival that was precarious at best. If, though, the last Kith ship but theirs drifted dead among the stars; or the few hundred aboard the Golden Flyer and the four on this world whose name was lost were the final remnants of the human race—she was bright and gentle and swayed sweetly when she walked.

“I—” He untangled his tongue. “I’m glad you did. How are you?”

“Lonely and frightened,” she confided. Cosmic interference seethed around her words. The fire spat sparks loudly into the darkness overhead. “If you don’t learn what went wrong here . . . . I don’t know if I can stand wondering the rest of my life.”

“Cut that!” he said sharply. The rusting of morale had destroyed more than one ship in the past. Although—“No, I’m sorry.” He knew she did not lack courage. The fear was alive in him too that he would be haunted forever by what he had seen here. Death in itself was an old familiar of the Kith. But this time they were returning from a past more ancient than the glaciers and the mammoths had been on Earth when they left. They needed knowledge as much as they needed air, to make sense of the universe. And their first stop in that spiral arm of the Galaxy which had once been home had confronted them with a riddle that looked unanswerable. So deep in history were the roots of the Kith that Jong could recall the symbol of the Sphinx; and suddenly he saw how gruesome it was.

“We’ll find out,” he promised Sorya. “If not here, then when we arrive at Earth.—Inwardly he was unsure. He made small talk and even achieved a joke or two. But afterward, laid out in his sleeping bag, he thought he heard the horn winding in the north.

The expedition rose at dawn, bolted breakfast, and stowed their gear in the spaceboat. It purred from the city on aerodynamic drive, leveled off, flew at low speed not far above ground. The sea tumbled and flashed on the right, the land climbed steeply on the left. No herds of large animals could be seen there. Probably none existed, with such scant room to develop in. But the ocean swarmed. From above Jong could look down into transparent waters, see shadows that were schools of fish numbering in the hundreds of thousands. Further off he observed a herd of grazers, piscine but big as whales, plowing slowly through a weed mat. The colonists must have gotten most of their living from the sea.

Regor set the boat down on a cliff overlooking the bay he had described. The escarpment ringed a curved beach of enormous length and breadth, its sands strewn with rocks and boulders. Kilometers away, the arc closed in on itself, leaving only a strait passage to the ocean. The bay was placid, dear bluish-green beneath the early sun, but not stagnant. The tides of the one big moon must raise and lower it two or three meters in a day, and a river ran in from the southern highlands. Mar Jong could see how shells littered the sand below high-water mark, proof of abundant life. It seemed bitterly unfair to him that the colonists had had to trade so much beauty for darkness.

Regor’s lean face turned from one man to the next. “Equipment check,” he said, and went down the list: fulgurator, communication bracelet, energy compass, medikit—“My God,” said Neri, “you’d think we were off on a year’s trek, and separately at that.”

“We’ll disperse, looking for traces,” Regor said, “and those rocks will often hide us from each other.” He left the rest unspoken: that that which had been the death of the colony might still exist.

They emerged into cool, flowing air with the salt and iodine and dean decay smell of coasts on every Earthlike world, and made their way down the scarp. “Let’s radiate from this point,” Regor said, “and if nobody has found anything, we’ll meet back here in four hours for lunch.”

Jong’s path slanted farthest north. He walked briskly at first, enjoying the motion of his muscles, the scrunch of sand and rattle of pebbles beneath his boots, the whistle of the many birds overhead. But presently he must pick his way across drifts of stone and among dark boulders, some as big as houses, which cut him off from the wind and his fellows; and he remembered Sorya’s aloneness.

Oh no, not that. Haven’t we paid enough? he thought. And, for a moment’s defiance: We didn’t do the thing. We condemned the traitors ourselves, and threw them into space, as soon as we learned Why should we be punished?

But the Kith had been too long isolated, themselves against the universe, not to hold that the sin and sorrow of one belonged to all. And Tomakan and his coconspirators had done what they did unselfishly, to save the ship. In those last vicious years of the Star Empire, when Earthmen made the Kithfolk scapegoats for their wretchedness until every crew fled to await better times, the Golden Flyer’s captured people would have died horribly—had Tomakan not bought their freedom by betraying to the persecutors that asteroid where two other Kith vessels lay, readying to leave the Solar System. How could they afterward meet the eyes of their kindred, in the Council that met at Tau Ceti?

The sentence was just: to go exploring to the fringes of the galactic nucleus. Perhaps they would find the Elder. Races that must dwell somewhere; perhaps they could bring back the knowledge and wisdom that could heal man’s inborn lunacies. Well, they hadn’t; but the voyage was something in itself, sufficient to give the Golden Flyer back her honor. No doubt everyone who had sat in Council was now dust. Still, their descendants—

Jong stopped in midstride. His shout went ringing among the rocks.

“What is it? Who called? Anything wrong?” The questions flew from his bracelet like anxious bees.

He stooped over a little heap and touched it with fingers that wouldn’t hold steady. “Worked flints,” he breathed. “Flakes, broken spearheads .. . shaped wood . . . something—” He scrabbled in the sand. Sunlight struck off a piece of metal, rudely hammered into a dagger. It had been, it must have been fashioned from some of the ageless alloy in the city—long ago, for the blade was worn so thin that it had snapped across. He crouched over the shards and babbled.

And shortly Mons’ deep tones cut through: “Here’s another site! An animal skull, could only have been split with a sharp stone, a thong—Wait, wait, I see something carved in this block, maybe a symbol—”

Then suddenly he roared, and made a queer choked gurgle, and his voice came to an end.

Jong leaped erect. The communicator jabbered with calls from Neri and Regor. He ignored them. There was no time for dismay. He tuned his energy compass. Each bracelet emitted a characteristic frequency besides its carrier wave, for location purposes, and—The needle swung about. His free hand unholstered his fulgurator, and he went bounding over the rocks.

As he broke out onto the open stretch of sand the wind hit him full in the face. Momentarily through its shrillness he heard the horn, louder than before, off beyond the cliffs. A part of him remembered fleetingly how one day on a frontier world he had seen a band of , huntsmen gallop in pursuit of a wounded animal that wept as it ran, and how the chief had raised a crooked bugle to his lips and blown just such a call.

The note died away. Jong’s glance swept the beach. Far down its length he saw several figures emerge from a huddle of boulders. Two of them carried a human shape. He yelled and sprinted to intercept them. The compass dropped from his grasp.

They saw him and paused. When he neared, Jong made out that the form they bore was Mons Rainart’s. He swung ghastly limp between his carriers. Blood dripped from his back and over his breast.

Jong’s stare went to the six murderers. They were chillingly manlike, half a meter taller than him, magnificently thewed beneath the naked white skin, but altogether hairless, with long webbed feet and fingers, a high dorsal fin, and smaller fins at heels and elbows and on the domed heads. The features were bony, with great sunken eyes and no external ears. A flap of skin drooped from pinched nose to wide mouth. Two carried flint-tipped wooden spears, two had tridents forged from metal—the tines of one were red and wet—and those who bore the body had knives slung at their waists.

“Stop!” Jong shrieked. “Let him go!”

He plowed to a halt not far off, and menaced them with his gun. The biggest uttered a gruff bark and advanced, trident poised. Jong retreated a step. Whatever they had done, he hated to—

An energy beam winked, followed by its thunderclap. The one who carried Mons’ shoulders crumpled, first at the knees, then down into the sand. The blood from the hole burned through him mingled with the spaceman’s, equally crimson.

They whirled. Neri Avelair pounded down the beach from the opposite side. His fulgurator spoke again. The shimmering wet sand reflected the blast. It missed, but quartz fused where it struck near the feet of the creatures, and hot droplets spattered them.

The leader waved his trident and shouted. They lumbered toward the water. The one who had Mons’ ankles did not let go. The body flapped arms and head as it dragged. Neri shot a third time. Jolted by his own speed, he missed anew. Jong’s finger remained frozen on the trigger.

The five giants entered the bay. Its floor shelved rapidly. In a minute they were able to dive below the surface. Neri reached Jong’s side and fired, bolt after bolt, till a steam cloud rose into the wind. Tears whipped down his cheeks. “Why didn’t you kill them, you bastard?” he screamed. “You could have gunned them down where you were!”

“I don’t know.” Jong stared at his weapon. It felt oddly heavy.

“They drowned Mons!”

“No . . . he was dead already. I could see. Must have been pierced through the heart. I suppose they ambushed him in those rocks—”

“M-m-maybe. But his body, God damn you, we could’a saved that at least!” Senselessly, Neri put a blast through the finned corpse.

“Stop that,” commanded Regor. He threw himself down, gasping for breath. Dimly, Jong noticed gray streaks in the leader’s hair. It seemed a matter of pity and terror that Regor Lannis the unbendable should be whittled away by the years.

What am I thinking? Mom is killed. Sorya’s brother.

Neri holstered his fulgurator, covered his face with both hands, and sobbed.

After a long while Regor shook himself, rose, knelt again to examine the dead swimmer. “So there were natives here,” he muttered. “The colonists must not have known. Or maybe they underestimated what savages could do.”

His hands ran over the glabrous hide. “Still warm,” he said, almost to himself. “Air-breathing; a true mammal, no doubt, though this male lacks vestigial nipples; real nails on the digits, even if they have grown as thick and sharp as claws.” He peeled back the lips and examined the teeth. “Omnivore evolving toward carnivore, I’d guess. The molars are still pretty flat, but the rest are bigger than ours, and rather pointed.” He peered into the dimmed eyes. “Human-type vision, probably less acute. You can’t see so far underwater. We’ll need extensive study to determine the color-sensitivity curve, if any. Not to mention the other adaptations. I daresay they can stay below for many minutes at a stretch. Doubtless not as long as cetaceans, however. They haven’t evolved that far from their land ancestors. You can tell by the fins. Of some use in swimming, but not really an efficient size or shape as yet.”

“You can speculate about that while Mons is being carried away?” Neri choked.

Regor got up and tried in a bemused fashion to brush the sand off his clothes. “Oh no,” he said. His face worked, and he blinked several times. “We’ve got to do something about him, of course.” He looked skyward. The air was full of wings, as the sea birds sensed meat and wheeled insolently close. Their piping overrode the wind. “Let’s get back to the boat. We’ll take this carcass along for the scientists.”

Neri cursed at the delay, but took one end of the object. Jong had the other. The weight felt monstrous, and seemed to grow while they stumbled toward the cliffs. Breath rasped in their throats. Their shirts clung to the sweat on them, which they could smell through every sea odor.

Jong looked down at the ugly countenance beneath his hands. In spite of everything, in spite of Mons being dead—oh, never to hear his big laugh again, never to move a chessman or hoist a glass or stand on the thrumming decks with him!—he wondered if a female dwelt somewhere out in the ocean who had thought this face was beautiful.

“We weren’t doing them any harm,” said Neri between wheezes.

“You can’t . . . blame a poison snake . . . or a carnivore . . . if you come too near,” Jong said.

“But these aren’t dumb animals! Look at that braincase. At that knife.” Neri needed a little time before he had the lungful to continue his fury: “We’ve dealt with nonhumans often enough. Fought them once in a while. But they had a reason to fight . . . mistaken or not, they did. I never saw or heard of anyone striking down utter strangers at first sight.”

“We may not have been strangers,” Regor said.

“What?” Neri’s head twisted around to stare at the older man.

Regor shrugged. “A human colony was planted here. The natives seem to have wiped it out. I imagine they had reasons then. And the tradition may have survived.”

For ten thousand years or more? Jong thought, shocked. What horror did our race visit on theirs, that they haven’t been able to forget in so many millennia?

He tried to picture what might have happened, but found no reality in it, only a dry and somehow thin logic. Presumably this colony was established by a successor civilization to the Star Empire. Presumably that civilization had crumbled in its turn. The settlers had most likely possessed no spaceships of their own;, outpost worlds found it easiest to rely on the Kith for what few trade goods they wanted. Often their libraries did not even include the technical data for building a ship, and they lacked the economic surplus necessary to do that research over again.

So—the colony was orphaned. Later, if a period of especially virulent anti-Kithism had occurred here, the traders might have stopped coming; might actually have lost any record of this world’s existence. Or the Kith might have become extinct, but that is not a possibility we will admit. The planet was left isolated.

Without much land surface it couldn’t support a very big population, even if most of the food and industrial resources had been drawn from the sea. However, the people should have been able to maintain a machine culture. No doubt their society would ossify, but static civilizations can last indefinitely.

Unless they are confronted by vigorous barbarians, organized into million-man hordes under the lash of outrage . . . . But was that the answer? Given atomic energy, how could a single city be overrun by any number of neolithic hunters?

Attack from within? A simultaneous revolt of every autochthonous slave? Jong looked back to the dead face. The teeth glinted at him. Maybe I’m soft-headed. Maybe these beings simply take a weasel’s pleasure in killing.

They struggled up the scarp and into the boat. Jong was relieved to get the thing hidden in a cold-storage locker. But then came the moment when they called the Golden Flyer to report.

“I’ll tell his family,” said Captain Ilmaray, most quietly.

But I’ll still have to tell Sorya how he looked, Jong thought. The resolution stiffened in him: We’re going to recover the body. Mons is going to have a Kithman’s funeral; hands that loved him will start him on his orbit into the sun.

He had no reason to voice it, even to himself. The oneness of the Kith reached beyond death. Ilmaray asked only if Regor believed there was a chance.

“Yes, provided we start soon,” the leader replied. “The bottom slopes quickly here, but gets no deeper than about thirty meters. Then it’s almost flat to some distance beyond the gate, farther than our sonoprobes reached when we flew over. I doubt the swimmers go so fast they can evade us till they reach a depth too great for a nucleoscope to detect Mons’ electronic gear.”

“Good. Don’t take risks, though.” Grimly: “We’re too short on future heredity as is.” After a pause, Ilmaray added, “I’ll order a boat with a high-powered magnascreen to the stratosphere, to keep your general area under observation. Luck ride with you.”

“And with every ship of ours,” Regor finished the formula.

As his fingers moved across the pilot board, raising the vessel, he said over his shoulder, “One of you two get into a spacesuit and be prepared to go down. The other watch the ‘scope, and lower him when we find what we’re after.”

“I’ll go,” said Jong and Neri into each other’s mouths. They exchanged a look. Neri’s glared.

“Please,” Jong begged. “Maybe I ought to have shot them down, when I saw what they’d done to Mons. I don’t know. But anyhow, I didn’t. So let me bring him back, will you?”

Neri regarded him for nearly a minute more before he nodded.

The boat cruised in slow zigzags out across the bay while Jong climbed into his spacesuit. It would serve as well underwater as in the void. He knotted a line about his waist and adjusted the other end to the little winch by the personnel lock. The metallic strand woven into its plastic would conduct phone messages. He draped a sack over one arm for the, well, the search object, and hoped he would not need the slugthrower at his hip.

“Mere!”

Jong jerked at Neri’s shout. Regor brought the craft to hoverhalt, a couple of meters above the surface and three kilometers from shore. “You certain?” he asked.

“Absolutely. Not moving, either. I suppose they abandoned him so as to make a faster escape when they saw us coming through the air.”

Jong clamped his helmet shut. External noises ceased. The stillness made him aware of his own breath and pulse and—some inner sound, a stray nerve current or mere imagination—the hunter’s horn, remote and triumphant.

The lock opened, filling with sky. Jong walked to the rim and was nearly blinded by the sunlight off the wavelets. Radiance ran to the horizon. He eased himself over the lip. The rope payed out and the surface shut above him. He sank.

A cool green roofed with sunblaze enclosed him. Even through the armor he felt multitudinous vibrations; the sea lived and moved, everywhere around. A pair of fish streaked by, unbelievably graceful. For a heretical instant he wondered if Mons would not rather stay here, lulled to the end of the world.

Cut that! he told himself, and peered downward. Darkness lurked below. He switched on the powerful flash at his belt.

Particles in the water scattered the light, so that he fell as if through an illuminated cave. More fish passed near. Their scales reflected like jewels. He thought he could make out the bottom now, white sand and uplifted ranges of rock on which clustered many-colored coraloids, growing toward the sun. And the swimmer appeared.

He moved slowly to the fringe of light and poised. In his left hand he bore a trident, perhaps the one which had killed Mons. At first he squinted against the dazzle, then looked steadily at the radiant metal man. As Jong continued to descend he followed, propelling himself with easy gestures of feet and free hand, a motion as lovely as a snake’s.

Jong gasped and yanked out his slugthrower. “What’s the matter?” Neri’s voice rattled in his earplugs.

He gulped. “Nothing,” he said, without knowing why. “Lower away.”

The swimmer came a little closer. His muscles were tense, mouth open as if to bite; but the deep-set eyes remained unwavering. Jong returned the gaze. They went down together.

He’s not afraid of me, Jong thought, or else he’s mastered his fear, though he saw on the beach what we can do.

Impact jarred through his soles. “I’m here,” he called mechanically. “Give me some slack and—Oh!”

The blood drained from his head as if an ax had split it. He swayed, supported only by the water. Thunders and winds went through him, and the roar of the horn.

“Jong!” Neri called, infinitely distant. “Something’s wrong, I know it is, gimme an answer, for the love of Kith!”

The swimmer touched bottom too. He stood across from what had belonged to Mons Rainart, the trident upright in his hand.

Jong lifted the gun. “I can fill you with metal,” he heard himself groan. “I can cut you to pieces, the way you—you—”

The swimmer shuddered (was the voice conducted to him?) but stayed where he was. Slowly, he raised the trident toward the unseen sun. With a single gesture, he reversed it, thrust it into the sand, let go, and turned his back. A shove of the great legs sent him arrowing off.

The knowledge exploded in Jong. For a century of seconds he stood alone with it.

Regor’s words pierced through: “Get my suit. I’m going after him.”

“I’m all right,” he managed to say. “I found Mons.”

He gathered what he could. There wasn’t much. “Bring me up,” he said.

When he was lifted from the bay and climbed through the air lock, he felt how heavy was the weight upon him. He let fall the sack and trident and crouched beside them. Water ran off his armor.

The doors closed. The boat climbed. A kilometer high, Regor locked the controls and came aft to join—the others. Jong removed his helmet just as Neri opened the sack.

Mons’ head rolled out and bounced dreadfully across the deck. Neri strangled a yell.

Regor lurched back. “They ate him,” he croaked. “They cut him to pieces for food. Didn’t they?”

He gathered his will, strode to the port, and squinted out. “I saw one of them break the surface, a short while before you came up,” he said between his teeth. Sweat—or was it tears?—coursed down the gullies in his cheeks. “We can catch him. The boat has a gun turret.”

“No—” Jong tried to rise, but hadn’t the strength.

The radio buzzed. Regor ran to the pilot’s chair forward, threw himself into it, and slapped the receiver switch. Neri set lips together, picked up the head, and laid it on the sack. “Mons, Mons, but they’ll pay,” he said.

Captain Ilmaray’s tones filled the hull: “We just got word from the observer’s boat. It isn’t on station yet, but the magnascreen’s already spotted a horde of swimmers . . . no, several different flocks, huge, must total thousands . . . converging on the island where you are. At the rate they’re going, they should arrive in a couple of days.”

Regor shook his head in a stunned fashion. “How did they know?”

“They didn’t,” Jong mumbled.

Neri leaped to his feet, a tiger movement. “That’s exactly the chance we want. A couple of bombs, dropped in the middle of ‘em.”

“You mustn’t!” Jong cried. He became able to rise too. The trident was gripped in his hand. “He gave me this.”

“What?” Regor swiveled around. Neri stiffened where he stood. Silence poured through the boat.

“Down below,” Jong told them. “He saw me and followed me to the bottom. Realized what I was doing. Gave me this. His weapon.”

“Whatever for?”

“A peace offering. What else?”

Neri spat on the deck. “Peace, with those filthy cannibals?”

Jong squared his shoulders_ The armor enclosing him no longer seemed an insupportable burden. “You wouldn’t be a cannibal if you ate a monkey, would you?”

Neri said an obscene word, but Regor suppressed him with a gesture. “Well, different species,” the pilot admitted coldly. “By the dictionary you’re right. But these killers are sentient. You don’t eat another thinking being.”

“It’s been done,” Jong said. By humans too. More often than not as an act of respect or love, taking some of the person’s mana into yourself. Anyway, how could they know what we were? When he saw I’d come to gather our dead, he gave me his weapon. How else could he say he was sorry, and that we’re brothers? Maybe he even realized that’s literally true, after he’d had a little while to think the matter over: But I don’t imagine their traditions are that old. It’s enough, it’s better, actually, that he confessed we were his kin simply because we also care for our dead.”

“What are you getting at?” Neri snapped.

“Yes, what the destruction’s going on down there?” Ilmaray demanded through the radio.

“Wait.” Regor gripped the arms of his chair. His voice fell low. “You don’t mean they’re—”

“Yes, I do,” Jong said. “What else could they be? How could a mammal that big, with hands and brain, evolve on these few islands? How could any natives have wiped out a colony that had atomic arms? I thought about a slave revolt, but that doesn’t make sense either. Who’d bother with so many slaves when they had cybernetic machines? No, the swimmers are the colonists. They can’t be anything else.”

“Huh?” grunted Neri.

Ilmaray said across hollow space: “It could be. If I remember rightly, Homo Sapiens is supposed to have developed from the, uh, Neandertaloid type, in something like ten or twenty thousand years. Given a small population, genetic drift, yes, a group might need less time than that to degenerate.”

“Who says they’re degenerate?” Jong retorted. Neri pointed to the staring-eyed head on the deck. “That does.”

“Was an accident, I tell you, a misunderstanding,” Jong said. “We had it coming, blundering in blind the way we did. They aren’t degenerate, they’re just adapted. As the colony got more and more dependent on the sea, and mutations occurred, those who could best take this sort of environment had the most children. A static civilization wouldn’t notice what was happening till too late, and wouldn’t be able to do anything about it if they did. Because the new people had the freedom of the whole planet. The future was theirs.”

“Yeah, a future of being savages.”

“They couldn’t use our kind of civilization. It’s wrong for this world. If you’re going to spend most of your life in salt water you can’t very well keep your electric machines; and flint you can gather almost anywhere is an improvement over metal that has to be mined and smelted.

“Oh, maybe they have lost some intelligence. I doubt that, but if they have, what of it? We never did find the Elder Races. Maybe intelligence really isn’t the goal of the universe. I believe, myself, these people are coming back up the ladder in their own way. But that’s none of our business.” Jong knelt and closed Mons’ eyes. “We were allowed to atone for our crime,” he said softly. “The least we can do is forgive them in our turn. Isn’t it? And . . . we don’t know if any other humans are left, anywhere in all the worlds, except us and these. No, we can’t kill them.”

“Then why did they kill Mons?”

“They’re air breathers,” Jong said, “and doubtless they have to learn swimming, like pinnipeds, instead of having an instinct. So they need breeding grounds. That beach, yes, that must be where the tribes are headed. A party of males went in advance to make sure the place was in order. They saw something strange and terrible walking on the ground where their children were to be born, and they had the courage to attack it. I’m sorry, Mons,” he finished in a whisper.

Neri slumped down on a bench. The silence came back.

Until Ilmaray said: “I think you have the answer. We can’t stay here. Return immediately, and we’ll get under weigh.”

Regor nodded and touched the controls. The engine hummed into life. Jong got up, walked to a port, and watched the sea, molten silver beneath him, dwindle as the sky hardened and the stars trod forth.

I wonder what that sound was, he thought vaguely. A wind noise, no doubt, as Mons said. But I’ll never be sure. For a moment it seemed to him that he heard it again, in the thrum of energy and metal, in the beat of his own blood, the horn of a hunter pursuing a quarry that wept as it ran.